welcome everyone to another QA on the
awakened from the meeting crisis discord
we've got John verb a key back thanks
John for being here
always a pleasure I want to just thank
you for all the live Q&A some of my my
friends an interlocutor it's like with
Paul and layman and Jordan and Chris
died they've been wonderful
appreciative of it and I know they have
enjoyed it very much
so I just wanted to thank you guys for
doing that I really like the direction
of that estate yeah we've been having a
great time with the the guests have all
been amazing they've been very generous
with their time and the questions have
been great
so we're yeah so and thank you for your
voices whisper Becky which have queued
them up so yeah this is a has been
fantastic so everyone how we've been
doing it if you could queue up your
questions in the event text which is the
text channel right above this channel if
you want me to read your question then
let me know otherwise I'll assume you
you want to read your own question now
we're gonna start off a little bit
different tonight so in the religion
that's not a religion structure channel
a bunch of our members have been working
very hard on a document where they've
been putting together basically a
proposed you know ideas for a proposed
structure developing the ideas for a
structure of the religion that's not a
religion and I sent it to John last week
and he's had a chance to look it over
and and so we like to start off by
chatting about that that for a little
bit and I think some of the people who
have been working on that are here I see
on tulip I'm sorry I never know how to
pronounce your name on Telestial this
here chef Ronnie is here the philistines
worked on it Strong's worked on it
started if I've missed missed anyone but
a lot of people have been working on
this document doing a fantastic job
so so can I first say something about it
in general Brent yeah absolutely go
ahead alright so first of all I was very
impressed by it I mentioned this to
Brett already and of course I'm going to
continue to work on this project to talk
about it Chris but in addition to the
carefulness and the sophistication of
the thought that I've seen here this
actually it also in tracked it in acts
and exemplify something that's really
important to me because how can I put
this I don't want this to be in my hand
I want to participate in your eyes to
try and create apologies of practices
and theoretical function around it but
this with you with with all of you this
is taking on a life of its own
beyond me and that is excellent because
that is exactly what it needs to be if
it's going to have any chance of
viability this has got to move to
something that over which I do not
exercising anything like ownership or
authorship I hope I get to always have
important a participatory role but the
fact that this is being taken up a
community in this vital and vibrant way
that's really that for me it is what is
most impressive about this document
again not to take away from both its
structure and its content which are
excellent but but the actual performance
of this and what it's enacting and
exemplifying because I think what is
most impressive to me about this thanks
so much for that I I know some of some
of the people are here are there any
questions that you guys want to bring up
with John about your document or draw
attention to certain points to discuss
yeah I think one question that I have
for you John is
do you think we're taking the right tack
and kind of discussing it and breaking
it down are we focusing on the right
things first
or are we maybe jumping the gun on
certain areas John I think you have a
fan in the background that's that's
making a bit of noise is Mihaly you're
muted but uh you fix the problem yeah
every I think it was another maybe
another member to so I think you're okay
go ahead okay so I would just put an
additional thing I mean there's the
concretization the conditions the
propositions obviously and they're
scaling it so and Retin are as an
unending process is fantastic but I
would I would welcome a category around
something like the ongoing dialogue or
discourse or reciprocal reconstruction
between but nar mag and science
particularly cognitive science one of
the things that I think that's not a
religion should be constantly because
you've got that it's an unending process
its open-ended but I think it should
always be responsive to what cognitive
science is telling us about our meaning
making machinery both within individual
and distributed cognition so I would
recommend that
as an addendum to that to what you've
done so far what do you think of as a
proposal I personally think it's great I
think there's been a lot of healthy
tension and conversation about the
relationship with science I think we've
probably spent an inordinate amount of
time talking about physics and all the
fun philosophical stuff that gets you
into a rabbit hole but ultimately I
think I think that's something that
makes a lot of sense kind of repairing
that relationship between the two or
[Music]
technologies and practices that was the
only thing that came to my mind as a
lacuna that I thought needed to be
addressed awesome it's great to hurt
anyone else
the Ritenour committee want to want to
jump in before we get to the general
questions I mean I have to be careful
with my time but I mean this project is
very good to me and again I don't I
don't want I'm not trying to reclaim
ownership and I definitely don't want to
be doing anything like that so what I'm
saying is in what wage can I be of
service to this project as it's
especially since it is taking on a life
of its own look at draft proposals or
talk to people and if feedback like
whatever I can do to help I mean I will
speak as a as a participant but I think
that is very much appreciated I think
your your involvement in it is something
that I think almost everyone wants I you
know again I don't think anyone would be
concerned with you trying to you know
grab the reins or anything like that I
think it's you know we respect you and
your work and so your your input is
certainly something that we dig into
heavy consideration or at least I can
speak for myself I know I do to ask my
collaboration Postum i guess one
question I'll ask is was there anything
specific that the draft that Brett
shared is there any kind of big
takeaways or points of feedback that you
have from what you've seen so far so
I've been talking about this with Tim
Bishop and this has been coming up too
and I think again it's an addendum to
the scaling thing so I've been talking
more and more about two things about
scalability and sustainability and what
would it take to make this not only
scalable but sustainable I don't mean in
terms of an idea because ideas have a
certain sustainability but as you know
as as a as a community of communities of
practice so that's also something that
it would be good if people started
turning their attention to I'm very
interested in the whole idea about how
this might not only move between sort of
layers of society etc of that but how I
don't want it I don't want it to fall
into the pattern sorry this language is
something so pretentious I'm really it
would be good if if this is succeeding
it would be good if it didn't fall prey
to what happened with you know with cops
work right you set up all of these
secular churches and it was very very
sort of popular during his lifetime and
then they quickly faded away as soon as
he was gone that's by the way why not
having this time to me in particular is
very very important to me so the issue
of sustainability might be one you want
to add to the Yale ability issue yeah I
think that's something that we've we've
had a lot of conversation about as well
because it to your point it's not just a
matter of scale it's kind of persisting
itself it's how do you keep it
continually evolving how do you make
sure it's not static that it kind of
retains that dynamic character in
essence and I think that's something
that it's a good point to call out that
that we should focus not just on the
scale that also and kind of be the
existence in perpetuity I'm taking
itself alive
yeah so yeah micki making it as
autopoietic as possible would be really
really welcome anything yen I think
we've also raised welcome I have sorry
I've raised the concern that as Ratna
grows we also need to put something in
place you prevent degeneration of
culture because as as it is now in this
server we've got a very good culture
operative and you know we're all just
trying to you know we're all striving
towards truth but I've seen that come
when communities grow too quickly for
instance yeah they they kind of invite a
load of like they don't acclimatize new
members to the wholesome culture quick
enough yeah which is you know Zack sign
because the ideas about trying to get a
clearer understanding of the
relationship between a revised notion of
Education and inculturation just what
you're talking about so what would be
lead educational aspects of this
community such that you know there is a
sustainable form of acculturation the
standards that make the community such a
success right now I think that's
important so and like I'm gonna be
talking was back again but it's gonna be
with a new exact but maybe you know even
if he's not on voices with the baby for
a while you might want to have him in
because um his ideas of my ideas are
very convergent but he's also that a lot
but a lot of part of the stuff that I
haven't quite as deeply about but his
idea of you know there's work on
education between two worlds I think
might be very relevant to it
very rather than oh yeah I can
definitely reach out to out to Zach to
see if it yeah see if he come on oh my
gosh a wonderful wonderful person but I
I mean I think that please don't
misunderstand me I don't think that's
like a comprehensive answer to the the
problem that was just brought up but I
think it's a good place to start to
wrestle with it John I had a follow-up
question to this about scaling and
degradation your lecture series really
changed my life and I would tell
everybody I knew about it and it was
interesting hearing some of the feedback
from some of my friends they come back
and be like well if you like you think
something significant it uses so many
big words what is this perspective on
this and then I would kind of try to put
it in like kind of worse precision like
kind of less signal words but people oh
right yeah and so I'm wondering just in
terms of scaling are there different
roles in terms of the signal-to-noise
the precision and could you maybe just
speak to that
how important are the words and the
quote unquote lies to children that
teachers use to get knowledge across
even in an advanced textbook on physics
you'll see a diagram of the atom that is
of course you know appreciably false
it's static it represents particles as
if they're little round spheres are
definite locations all kinds of stuff
that just turned out to be false but we
can't do without these diagrams because
we can't get people to understand how to
practice the physics without them I'm so
I think it's a you know indispensable
fictions that amplifier reality so that
we can see patterns that we otherwise
couldn't see I mean Plato did it first
with you know with the Republic and you
belong you do this city you blow up the
human psyche to the level of a city so
you might see things that you otherwise
wouldn't see well I think this is a
comprehensive thing we first
have acknowledged as part of at all
levels children to adults we're doing
this so there's more of a continuum
there so that that's the first thing I
would say secondly I've been trying to
think about this and there's somebody I
have a recording with him and I'm going
to put it on poisons with her baby and
this is this is Zeke's working now he
took a bunch of mine I think it's the
first 16 or 17 of the videos and he made
15 minute animated versions of the
arguments and I think they are massively
successful it's on big animation and
like I said I'll release the video in a
bit and then perhaps you could also have
EMR voices with verve a key because
people that they can view that are
really important I'm also meeting with
ethos Amanda because he approached me
and said I want to do a bunch of videos
with you we've done five release one so
far we've done another what's about
trying to make it simple without of
course making it stupid so I hate this
project very seriously but I think I
think it's doable
I think the work that Zeke did on think
big animation have you seen any of those
videos they're they're excellent and I
think they're really really excellent
taking you know they don't of course
they can't capture all of the argument
but they get the core and then they
present it in a multi like a multi
excellency multi modal but that will be
confusing that's a term from psychology
it's both aphasia but there's a visual
presentation as well as just a verbal
presentation because it's animated that
really improves the intelligibility and
the accessibility of it so I think that
there is first of all a way of
philosophically grounding this in the
work of people like Eldon and others you
know true like I said the book true or
not and then linking that to the
specific project of creating these these
bridging forms and I take
I take Zeke's work on think big
animation as exemplary of how to do
exactly that have any of you seen it and
they need the videos I I haven't so
that's definitely something he yeah he
did I think he went all the way up to
Agustin in connection in the series
excellent alright so we have some
questions queued up so helix and you
have a question he likes you
okay all right now so if religio is like
the spirituality of religion where is
the spirituality in religion and what
else is there besides spirituality in
religion is the way in which you have
rituals for accessing and activating and
accentuating the jail and celebrating
that hello sorry my computer was having
a bit of technical difficulty I actually
missed it did you start asking my
question I did but but did you if you
want to say it in your own way yeah do
you mind yeah go ahead
thank you thank you so much but before I
get to my question John I briefly met
you in Kingston Ontario and you were
wondering about the state of your tenure
and I heard that you actually got it so
I just really wanted to congratulate you
on that that's really special that you
got then the screening room I I went up
to and you were sitting alone I shook
your hand I tried to get as many
questions as I could at you
that was a lot of fun that day we are
doing another one in denim clothes
Tobin struck but maybe we'll do another
one at some point anyway would be
awesome yes okay so a few of us were
talking about religio last night and I
was feeling a bit confused about it and
so we we kind of came to somewhat of a
conclusion I just wanted to hear your
thoughts on it so if religio is like the
spirituality of religion where is the
spirituality and religion specifically
and what else would there be besides
spirituality in religion yes so I think
that the spirituality in religion is you
know the set the set the set of ritual
practices that are designed to access
activate accentuate and celebrate
religio both individually and
collectively and I think that whereas
spirituality tends to point more towards
an individual individual cognition
religion tends to point more towards
distributed cognition and what what
layman calls overflow and I think that's
correct
I think spirituality also I notice that
I'm putting them on a continuum right I
think this virtuality puts more of an
emphasis on the cultivation of wisdom
and it tends to put more of an emphasis
on the cultivation of worship that the
idea that people are getting into a
right relationship of proper reverence
towards what is ultimate and that
doesn't have to be supernatural there
are religions that don't have a super
naturalistic element in them and I think
religion also that's a lot more work
than spirituality does in
the problems of scalability and
sustainability and in order to do that I
think religion does a lot more work on
creating you know pictures and
propositions that are supposed to
constrained individual spirituality so
that the group spirituality is all it's
always available I'm still scratching my
head on what religio is even though that
was a beautiful demonstration of maybe
the difference between spirituality and
religionists Oh
intended to designate the no
spirituality or spiritual practices
religion religio is supposed to
designate the sense of connectedness
that relevance realization affords us
the way the agent in the arena of belong
together and generate affordances
generate participatory now knowing that
grounds respect title knowing and the
fact that that for adaptive reasons that
sense of connectedness comes with it
comes with very powerful effective and
motivational processes attached to it we
seek out connectedness and we are
distressed when we lose the conductive
mist and so the religio over the Latin
word religio originally means to bind
things together to connect things
together but I'd show in the word
precisely because I think what is exact
it and appreciated in all the senses of
the word appreciated on all the work on
senses the word appreciation what is
exactly and appreciated in religion and
even in spirituality is religio I think
when we are trying to use individual
practices of transformation and the
cultivation of wisdom to enhance religio
that spirituality when we're doing that
plus the other things that I said go
into
mijin I think that's what religion is so
I don't think of religion itself as
spirituality I think when we use mythos
rituals stories sets of practices so
that we could pursue religio for its own
sake rather than extra mentally for our
cognitive agency survival so the analogy
I use is your capacity for hearing sound
to being connected to Sal that's like
religio music is spirituality music is
playing with the machinery by which you
are connected to the sound making it
intelligible all right so you have a lot
of adaptive advantage the degree to
which you can make sounds intelligible
to you and connect via sound to your
environment and so you have all this
machinery for making your ability to
hear work very well but sometimes you
step apart from that and you go you play
with the machinery of hearing and you
listen to music if you play with the
machinery of hearing and salience and
you're doing it for its own sake
precisely because it's intrinsically
valuable to you because it carries with
all all of this motivational and
effective power so if you know if sound
you know the ability to hear is religio
as in the analogy but the ability to
listen to music is spirituality and then
the ability to do it with a bunch of
people make music together would be
religion how's that but that's really
good and I just want to concretize to
see if I understand it to use technology
as an example if religio is the sense of
connectedness or how to connect with
technology then be a form of
spirituality because it's a mechanism to
connect or with technology be a form of
religio I think when we're doing things
like this when we turn right when we're
enhancing
the technology to enhance the religio
for its own sake it's celebrating it the
way we're doing here I think now it's
started to move into spirituality hmm
thank you that was great in John 3 is it
possible that you get a little bit
closer to your mic it's just yeah you're
sounding a little distant
I think what's doing that is this yeah
yes that's better thank you
so tell me you but you know the question
kill me I'm kill me I'm kind of new to
your work John but I must have Kelly
Meyers on YouTube just I'm really
grateful for your work of course and I
see this discovery of your community in
your work as sort of like a mile marker
on the path that I've been on so I'm
pretty happy to be diving in but um
I wonder thank you I wanted to thank you
for the questions you've been Kelley's
been in the Sangha for the morning
classes of meditation and contemplation
the cultivation of wisdom I just wanted
to thank you your questions are often I
think very valuable to the rest of their
valuable to me but I get a very clear
sense that they're valuable to other
people who are attending the session so
thank you very much for that oh you're
welcome and thank you for taking
questions I think that's very important
for building the community so it's
definitely mutually appreciated I guess
I typed my question out so I guess I'll
read it but just to preface that this
has kind of been churning in my mind
from a lot of the ideas from people like
for example Brett Weinstein has been
making me think about these things so I
don't know if you've already discussed
it somewhere but I've been thinking
about the idea of leadership yeah
so my question is how you see leadership
fitting within the framework and
observations in awakening from the
meeting crisis and and your other
discussions so I'm thinking that the
process of reciprocal opening would be
like contributing to the skills you need
for leadership but I'm also wondering if
the
assesses associated with the meaning
crisis itself is is perhaps like a
driver of poor leadership and lack of
leadership in our societies and I guess
as an example I feel like I'm not like a
leader so to speak but now I with your
ideas it occurred to me that that might
be my way I'm interacting with the world
is just not giving me its narrowing me
into where I can't be a leader I don't
see my ideas as being worth having
confidence in I guess so maybe you could
just sort of speak about that maybe
starting with like a definition of
leadership because I really don't know
that I have a firm grasp on really what
it is and like a scientific sense so I
mean so I'm crystal that's a fantastic
question
and it's it's a question that
unfortunately I haven't put as much time
into in order to give you a deep answer
the question is deep and so what I'm
what I'm what I want to do is indicate
first of all my ignorance because of
lack of work because I have concentrated
on something that is close enough to
that that it takes my attention which
I've been concentrating a lot on the
question of what it is to be a good
teacher because I'm a teacher and
therefore that has taken out when I'm
what I'm sort of thinking about the
relationship I tend to and I don't think
this is correct
so I'm admitting a mistake I tend to
assimilate
I think unconsciously the question of
leadership to the question of mentorship
and the question of pedagogy and that's
a mistake so this is something I've got
to put more thought into I have put some
thought into it but only in a negative
fashion in that I'm very concerned with
the way in which all of us I mean the
community I don't I'm sorry I'm not
trying to be presumptuous I mean I the
people I'm talking to like Jordan and I
there's there's a model here that Weber
would call a charismatic leadership and
the thing about that is that seems to
fit naturally with
the kinds of communities where we're
really emphasizing emergence and
innovation and transformational and
charismatic leadership right it was
emphasized a lot by Weber so charisma is
basically and this is coming out of
discussion I'm having with Jennifer
stellar and some of the people on are a
charismatic leader has the capacity I
would say to introduce something like
awe or wonder into people but also
resolve it for them so that they don't
slip into horror or a sense of
disconnection or a sense of being
overwhelmed and and so they tend to
trigger a kind of reverence because
reverence is the virtue for responding
to I would argue and and and I think and
I think so charismatic leadership is so
closely associated with communities
where emergence and innovation are
emphasized precisely because that form
of leadership puts a hype it gets its
existence out of inducing wonder and
insight and transformation in people so
that makes sense to me but the issue
that I have typically is that
charismatic leadership is also the one
that has the greatest potential to feed
into narcissism to feed into a sort of
dangerous four versions of popular
populism and things like that so I'm
sorry Kelly I know this is not a
complete answer I'm just and I've
already told you I put in adequate work
in and I made note I'm trying to show
you the all I'm doing is showing you
where I have put thought in and so that
the the alternative to the dangers of
charismatic leadership of course is
institutional leadership where people
have authority to lead because of the
office that they have achieved through
some kind of meritocracy whether or not
it's a real meritocracy or are just a
sham one but whatever now the advantages
of institutional leadership is it's very
it's very it's it's much harder
for it to go off the rails into sort of
a cult-like thing but the disadvantages
of institutional leadership is precisely
that we lose an orientation towards
emergence and innovation and so I'm
trying to understand is there a way in
which we could get what I saw with the
scientists who are doing the work with
the Rovers on Mars and I've talked about
this in a couple of my talks and it's in
some of the work I'm doing with in
chianti they have this style of
leadership in which there's a constantly
shifting form of leadership and it's
constantly shifting between expertise
and something like a charismatic style
like is there a way in which we can
create a dynamic small world network
organization of people in which we can
sort of get the best or split the
difference between institutional
leadership and charismatic leadership
and so that's a question that's on my
mind because it's I think it's integral
to trying to prevent a lot of what we're
working on here together from going off
in some very dangerous directions with
and again we are we have to we all me
and we also be careful of it's because
we're we're in situations of you know an
emphasis on emergence and innovation and
transformation and you know there and
and we are I think rightfully so
appreciative of charismatic individuals
who are sources of insight and
innovation you have to be very careful
about the dangers of narcissism
inflation hubris and
the degeneration into a cult but I also
don't want to just go and say well then
we have to go into institutional
leadership because that's got us a lot
of the problems that we're trying to
break out of so sorry that was a bit
rambling but as I said my thought and
this is very immature and I'm just
trying to give you what what thought I
have had about leadership right now
well that's definitely
I mean trysting idea is that I think I
think it actually clarifies one thing
that I was referring to with what brett
weinstein talks about he kind of
identified what i think is the same a
same trend that you're pointing out
india the concept of charismatic
leadership he's identified that many
would-be leaders are what he says are
trapped in the gig economy and so that
kind of feeds into that but i do wonder
because as a society we need
institutions and so i wonder if i would
encourage you to maybe still define that
balance because like for instance anyone
who joins the religion that's not a
religion maybe we would want them to
transform into someone who could be
suited to lead our society you know i I
was only I am oriented towards the
balance I think what Paul said about you
know individuals
innovate but institutions preserve right
and so I think that's very that's very
relevant I guess I guess I tended to
overemphasize the charismatic in my
presentation to you because that's
that's that's my own self self
reflection and self criticism I am
concerned about that about falling into
that myself and so I tend to give that a
lot more a little bit more priority in
my thinking right now so thank you
that's why all right next up is Jack
hello my question is it can be quite
overwhelming sometimes to have a chronic
condition that is rather disabling and
disorienting and it can be hard to
softly communicate with maybe the part
of our body where the chronic condition
resides or to integrate communication
throughout the body you feel like a
blockage and
I'll be able to have anger that results
especially if you have a chronic
condition at a young age when your body
is supposed to be spry and young and
particularly when the chronic condition
is flaring badly yeah it can be easy to
garner a lot of anxiety
if freaking out rather than doing the
right thing which would be to go through
it I was in mindfully so what are some
techniques that we can apply okay so I
can speak to this personally if you
don't mind because I think that's that's
the kind of response that's needed here
I suffer from a chronic condition I
suffer from an ears disease hello are
you so there yeah sorry sorry III suffer
from the nearest disease this is a is
this a chronic condition it's incurable
in which my inner ear will inexplicably
fill up with fluid it will cause me pain
dizziness a loss of hearing vertigo and
often tremendous vertigo like fall down
vertigo or I will fall down and so the
Meniere's disease also leaves me with
unremitting tecna's s in my left ear and
because of the way aversive conditioning
happens once I have an attack or two I
get very powerful agoraphobia because it
becomes very difficult for me to go
outside because part of my brain is
trying to keep me inside where I'm safe
in case I get an attack and so I that I
have to not only challenge the initial
onset of an attack and the I would
rather have an iPad and pain I've been
in a hospital and I was it looked like
like I was potentially going to die from
an infection and I've had intense pain I
would take that over a Meniere's attack
any day of the week and then so I don't
only have to deal with that I have to
deal with the the very the very rapid
way in which in conditions of
agoraphobia
to challenge that continually so and
then as you said this goes into my
sitting every time I said there is
there's a lot of body armor in the left
side of my head and my neck and my body
because there's a part of me that's
always trying to be hyper vigilant for
my my ear deal with the pain right so
all of this is ongoing for me so I
understand
very very directly and clearly what
you're talking about
so what that has meant for me is first
of all I don't want to sound trite but
when I get remission and I get times in
which I'm not as challenged by many
years I think of those as the most
important times for my practice
precisely because my practice won't be
as deep when the when I get a flare-up
and then I try to adjust it accordingly
I try to reduce so you know there's a I
teach like a progression of skills in
the course on the mindfulness practice
and when I having a flare-up
I don't pursue the deepest most profound
practices I drop back down to the basic
practices that I have practiced the
longer and therefore have have a lot of
stability to them I also practice with
making my reaction in my body to the
veneers not the veneers itself but my
reaction my embodied and in mind it the
way my mind is tense and tries to ignore
that and the way my body is tense and
tries to control it all of that
secondary reaction and some of the
emotion around it like the attendant
anxiety I sometimes will make that the
especially when I'm not in the middle of
an intense flare-up I will make that the
object of my meditation and I will or I
will direct Metta towards it or
four passionate towards it and again not
with the intent of curing it or making
it go away the disease but realizing
that the secondary reaction is something
over which I bear responsibility and
that I can learn to let go of and that's
oh I I can make a space again not for
cure because what I have is not curable
but I can make a space for more adaptive
responses that are more consonant with
my longitudinal ability to engage in the
practices I want to engage in what was
that at all helpful because I'm deeply
sympathetic with what you're talking
about yes though is helpful do you want
to follow up question because I mean I
take this what you're saying very
seriously I mean it's the the the
agoraphobia part like it's hard to can
be hard to go out and they can get easy
to develop a lot of anxiety about yeah
what's gonna happen yeah there is that
mean if there's no access to help or
something so I need part of what I've
tried to I tried to do is I've tried to
do imaginative exercise to say well what
would happen if I like as I have had
attacks when I'm out and they've often
so this it's human these are very bad at
what's called affective forecasting
we're very bad at actually predicting
our effective response to situation and
what the circumstances will be in that
situation and so one of the things that
I've done is I've tried to collect
instances where I've been out and there
I've had an attack like I try to sort of
create them as memorials and as bad as
they were that wasn't so bad like so
when I started teaching here let me give
you a concrete example when I started
teaching the mindfulness class I was
very worried about having a Meniere's
attack
as I was teaching it because I thought
that would be very disruptive and of
course I did have one and then I
realized no the what what rather than
people sort of abandoning me when I
shared it with him and I shared how the
practice is helpful to me and how it can
be a chronic illness can be integrated
with the practice I got a tremendous
amount of support that that doesn't mean
I didn't have another attack because I
did but what it meant was all the the
huge narrative that I built around the
narrative of rejection and the rejection
and the narrative of failure I was able
to address that pretty comprehensively
and so building up a you know because
you can't do it when you're in
rumination you can't do it when you're
in rumination building up outside
illumination a record of where you have
been outside and there his right either
virtually or or literally and there has
been an attack and you are nevertheless
right it hasn't been as terrifyingly bad
as your fear makes it seem I have found
that a very helpful technique right mark
you've got a question for John hello
John good thank you again I / - staying
late last time for my question even
though you didn't know it was mine so
that was nice hey it's great to hear
from you as always I want to thank you
for all of the ways you contribute to
the Sangha I'm glad I can be of some of
some service there it's a lot of fun and
I really appreciate the lessons I'm
learning a lot and my question is
actually kind of about this so there's
two sort of core problems that I've
always had in terms of that I've always
seen with meditation one is engagement
right it's hard to get people to agree
to do it put in the work and spend the
time but even when they do that a large
number of people seem to fail to get
mostly what I'm referring to is the
second-order effects out of it
um you know that the stuff you talk
about around people see you and they
they ask you if something's changed
about you sort of stuff and so I've
broken this down into so one of the
things I think mission bring you
specifically is bringing you with
perspectival flexibility yeah and that's
just engagement right if you engage you
should get that just following the steps
or following some method but then the
other end of this is something I'm sort
of playing with as an idea called
engaging in continuous sampling and the
engagement and continuous sampling would
be something like the ability to do the
integration of the meditation into your
into the rest of your life ya know so
this is more of a cog side question
which is one reason why I didn't ask it
in the meditation itself so I'm
wondering if you have any answers in or
pointers in terms of how we can
facilitate the meditation experience
integration more easily and make it more
accessible for people technique is a
technique that's being used in
psychology and cognitive science as a
way of trying to get that that deeper
transformation that you're talking about
the second-order effects is I like that
we call it naming them by the way so I
mean so you know you're aware of the
traditional thing the traditional thing
is you know the practice of the precepts
and regularly practicing the integration
as you come out of the practice and then
the tradition also talks about you know
creating the triggers specific
situations putting things in your pocket
or some people have timers that go off
periodically and when that happens you
know you do the one or two breath
meditation and you do their right and
then you see which aspect
of mindfulness could be applied in this
situation and then you also do the other
when you do spontaneously have insight
or flexibility or somebody notes that in
you you take a moment to write it down
and note it down because relying on your
memory is it won't work it won't work it
won't work
oh yeah I'll remember that New York very
well so I think trying to create
triggers throughout the day in
conjunction with doing the integration
practices that the promises and making
the commitment on a regular basis
especially in a state that bridges out
of a seated or moving practice I think
that having the ecology of practices and
especially having moving practices or
trains the brain to apply mindfulness in
interaction as opposed to just being
inside an introspective space I think
that's I know for me that the places
where the transfers happen first were
the places that were afforded by the Tai
Chi Chuan rather than the Vipassana
itself or the meta so I there's a lot of
things we could do sorry there's a lot
of things that have been recommended by
the tradition and I just imagined them
to you I think with that there are some
existing apps out there that are also
designed to both sample people get them
to quickly record and also to provoke
them to do moments of integration so I
think I think it's possible that we have
an ecology of practices we could also
bootstrap a lot of the traditional ways
of practicing integration and probably
improve their efficacy
all right strong
sterling you're up you're up next and
you've got I think three questions here
but we're running quickly low on time so
could you please just stick to one
they're all connected those I think John
can answer them together but I wanted to
ask about suchness and mones within the
context of engineering symbolic
sufficiency so the three that I went to
the connectors is such nice two
thickness as mones is to nothingness and
then does such nurse speak to the parts
and monas speak to the holes such that
one can refer to discrete parts and
continuous holes and then finally I was
reading up on Chinese metaphysics and I
discovered that we way has an opposite
you way and if you're familiar with you
way could you tell me if you way is the
suchness as Wu way is to Moniz yeah so I
don't know about you where I would like
to know more about that that's the first
time anybody's ever mentioned it to me I
mean 29 years of practice so that's
pretty astonishing well done for you
that's great so I'd like to know more
about that so I can't comment on the
third but the sexiness to thickness and
the and the more nests to noting this
that I get that right is that the way
matter right so let me work with that
one because I think that stuff that I
think there's a reason why you presented
that first because I think that's the
foundational one um so I can't let's see
I tend to think the such nurse as the
mystery that is founded individuation
and the morning as the mystery that's
disclosed in participation I definitely
think of what suchness
moving like yeah moving into
instantiation and whereas the morning is
moving into not instantiation but
something more like emanation I mean in
a sense of eternity I yeah I think if if
we take if we take thing this as it was
always the name of in
the middle of Middle Ages with it was a
say city I can't remember the term but
what mate would actually mean something
a particular thing and in that sense
they were trying to get out what made it
a non repeatable non categorical raw
individual that was instantiated
in that sense of thickness I would
yeah relate such nesting this and and
I'm using the word fingers here the word
you use because I'm hoping that we're
agreeing that we're not identifying
things with object we're not about
identifying thickness with objects I'm
identifying thinness with uh you know
the instantiation of of a raw individual
and so the and the morning with the no
thickness yes that makes sense to me too
yeah because the morning is what's
opening towards yeah the the the I don't
I'm struggling for adjectives here but
the the the sense of the ground by which
all intelligibility emerges or emanates
whichever when you want to talk about
yeah the more I think on this the more I
like it if again we don't identify
thinness with being an object because I
don't think that's the same and we don't
have identified no thickness with being
some kind of secret amorphous substance
behind everything the data well the the
thickness I think we'll have to
negotiate a bit further but I think
mostly on board with that
and then just very quickly would you say
that such nurse refers to discrete part
and mourners to continuous holes the
discrete and continuous dichotomy is
there what I'm getting it I don't know I
mean there's a sense in which it's right
but I I have the time I've been reading
what are the Aeneid but one of the
Aeneid on on the intelligible right and
he goes on and on about the dangers of
understand individuation and
determination in spatial terms because
we're taking something that's altered
this is what this is this is why I'm
sort of resisting identifying thickness
with objects because objects are
typically well maybe not maybe if you
think about Wharton's hyper objects but
objects and that comes up in the
contrast with hyper objects objects are
spatially defined and I'm really
hesitant to understand as' in terms of
spatial distinctions like Parkman Hall
now he does propose that it's possible
to think of partner Hall in non spatial
terms and I'm really trying to wrap my
head around what that means and he has a
lot of confidence that he is making
sense and I get glimmers of that so
sorry strong this is going to be sort of
a dodgy answer but it's an honest answer
insofar insofar as I think the thickness
if you're trying to talk about the way
individuation is a particular determine
that a particular determination a
determinate Ness and in that sense a
boundedness but but but not identifying
that with spatial localization and
limitation then I would say yes to what
you just said okay yeah I think the same
page and it'll be very useful for future
questions as well so thank you very much
sorry sorry I did I was hoping to i hope
mark is still here because i wanted to
know if mark I found my answer to his
question helpful yeah I'm I'm here I
think the next of the meditative
practices John that that answer was was
pretty helpful and and if I can indulge
a follow-up I was curious if Karzai and
particular has anything to say about
that process sort of outside of the
moving practices and meditation for so
for people who can't or won't engage
with meditation want you to give them
that that
continuous sampling that integration
phase yeah so that's a really good
question
hey I mean so there's a lot of
discussion about transfer appropriate
processing and how you get people to
transfer and creating what are called
implementation plans and and
implementation plans have this right
this is how you get people to pursue
long term goals and the difficulty
within a good implementation plan is
it's actually it has to get this sweet
spot there's balance between giving
people a whole sequence of our
benchmarks that they move towards but it
has to be integrated with giving them
ongoing immediately appliable coping
strategies because people also tend to
abandon these things when they hit
difficulties or problems which they
can't cope with so I think the issue I
think what you're drawing out from me
which i think is very helpful the issue
isn't only triggering people like I
talked about to you before but the issue
is how can we afford transfer and that's
not just transfer that's how do we give
people the right balance between a sort
of schedule of goals and ongoing a
capacity for coping with unexpected
difficulties and challenges and that
that is something that I try to think
about as a teacher and I try to think
about the degree to which modeling helps
people with coping whereas involvement
to a an ongoing community helps people
with long term goals so that's what I'm
trying to get a bit of an answer there
perfect thank you thank you
Brad I can take one more question and
then I gotta go if that's so good
all right okay actually I and I sorry I
know there are a lot of people with
questions but I just actually like to
give Laureen a chance to ask a question
she is running she just started running
a weekly study group on the weekend from
the meaning crisis and she had coming
out of that chlorine or the rain is it
Laureen did I hear you correctly is that
correct yes Lert all right oh wait she
gone
no she is oh you know okay I'm gonna I'm
gonna read it out it's just coming from
the study group discussion of episode
three of waking from the meaning crisis
continuous cosmos and modern grant
grammar can you tell us more about myths
and the relevance of grammar as a psycho
technology in our discussion I somehow
concluded that myths or stories and the
usage of the past present and future
tenses grammar is relevant to inspire
creative insight and then and the call
to action okay so I should first of all
note when I'm talking about grammar
their cultural cognitive grammar I'm
using it as a by analogy I'm using it
the way sort of Dickens time did I'm not
talking about sort of linguistic grammar
but so I'm not clear on what you said
because your question could be mean that
but I'm talking more about cognitive
grammar I'm talking about the
constraints on on conceptual generation
conceptual linkage and the connections
between link' concepts and perception
and practices so I'm talking about
something that's not specifically a
linguistic phenomena and how I think
about myths is I think about them yes
very much as stories but there are they
are stories that have a central symbolic
and ritual aspect to them and this week
I talked about this much later in the
series so this isn't just promise
they'll be more there for you in the
series on this that I think a symbol has
a symbol is something that affords
communication it affords a relationship
between what's inside our current
framing and what's outside of it and
beyond it so one in one instance it's
not should not be reduced to this one
instance of where we need symbols is in
the relationship between our conscious
and our unconscious processing because
what comes into consciousness has been
framed in a particular way and often
where where we're ignoring important
aspects of the environment that need to
be brought in but it's unconscious to us
so we need a symbol that bridges between
the unconscious and the conscious or the
symbol can bridge between our everyday
way of framing things and experiences we
might have within flow or mystical
experience to get us a sense of a more
encompassing and deeper contact with
reality that's very hard to put into
words and we need to symbolically relate
it or symbols are very important and I
talked about this much later in the
series in bridging between my framing of
who I am now and my aspiration to who I
want to be so there's many ways in which
symbols bridge between things that we
have a sort of clear grasp on and things
that we only have the things that we're
only extending towards in our in our
relevance realization and
intelligibility so myths are stories in
which symbols play a crucial role for
getting us into aspiration or getting
the unconscious and the conscious to
talk to each other or getting our
everyday experience to talk to our
transformative experiences and miss
present these symbol these symbols in a
way that is perennial II attracted to us
that's what I meant when I said miss
aren't about ancient stories from the
past they're about ways of
Bhalla CLE activating our cognition so
that we are capable of picking up on
patterns that are otherwise not not
intelligible or not visible or disclosed
to us and so that's why myth it's always
bound up with some kind of ritual
practice some kind of regular and
reliable practice by which people are
trying to transform consciousness
cognition character and communitas
because symbols are only grasped
that's not even quite the right words
symbols are only living to you they're
only alive in you when they are bound up
with when they are affording and are
bound up with processes of
transformation and so I think that what
symbols do sort what myths do are create
stories that put together dramas of
ritual and symbol that actually
transform our cognitive cultural grammar
so that we can aspire so that we can uh
that we can engage in self transcendence
so that we can come to a more fuller
form of interest psychic communication
between the conscious and the
unconscious mind that's why I take myth
so deeply seriously when I even wonder
about the possibility of post narrative
or trans narrative myth myth that
doesn't rely on narrative structures the
work that Sally mukbang does on parables
and the way a parable looks like it's a
narrative and it draws you into
narrative thinking and then it blows it
apart and undermines it it explodes it
so that you move into a trans narrative
transformation like the myth of the
prodigal son they're very Sufi myths I'm
very interested in the possibility that
myth might not be necessarily tied to
narrative but typically it has been
typically it has been so that's that's
that's my answer to that question
excellent question and like I say there
is a lot more discussion
both in the series later episodes of the
series in the plane the zombie book in
work I'm doing with Chris Christopher
Master Pietro on this topic of myth it
is an inexhaustible topic as it rightly
should be well thank you so much once
again for another great Q&A the
questions were all great and your answer
is obviously just as engaging as ever
well thank you so much for your time
tonight thank you so much I mean I'm
kind of humbled by this by this
community and I'm sorry I don't mean
that is false modesty I mean it I'm
grateful and I'm appreciative and I'm
impressed and I just I guess I'm
expected pressing the hope that I can
sort of live up to the sense of
responsibility I have to how rich
already this community is and becoming
it or not this is not flattery I mean it
and so thank you thank you so much and
and my strongest encouragement to all of
you to keep going on this because there
is something you know precious there's a
pearl of great price here that we you
know we need to we need to savor and
treasure so thank you very very much
thank you everybody and thank you John
and and everyone to tonight we've got at
9 o'clock Eastern
we've got virtual conversations going
which is sort of like an authentic
relating type practice that learning is
running at 10:00 yeah yeah 10:00 p.m.
we've got a shadow dance which is an
ecstatic dance session that Kali is
running and we've got a lot of other
great events through up throughout the
week so please everyone in the
announcements channel the pinned post
has a link to our Google Calendar so
we're having more and more events we're
experimenting with rituals we're
experimenting with different types of
psycho technologies so they're coming
all the time
all right well I'm gonna go so thank you
everybody thank you very much bye-bye
thanks John and thanks everyone says
it's Tyler thanks Tyler for yes Thank
You Tyler Tyler I'd like to talk to you
again sometime soon please absolutely
John I'll reach out okay thank you very
much oh thank you all right thanks
everyone that was great I'm sorry
there's so many questions and there's an
it's relatively little time so I'm sorry
you can't get to everyone John's answers
are always so complete so there's a
there's a cost/benefit there we we don't
get quite as many questions but we get
great answers so so please bring your
questions I'll try to prioritize next
week the people who didn't get to or in
two weeks so the people we didn't get to
today so and remind me maybe in the
questions and cueing up the questions
next time that you didn't get to ask
tonight and so we'll try to make sure
everyone gets chance